<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><generator uri="http://jekyllrb.com" version="3.1.6">Jekyll</generator><link href="/atom.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2018-01-14T15:31:15-05:00</updated><id>/</id><title>Generally Biology</title><subtitle>A blog about computer science, biology, and everything else</subtitle><entry><title>A Brief History of Bioinformatics?</title><link href="/writing/ABriefHistoryOfBioinformatics/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="A Brief History of Bioinformatics?" /><published>2017-03-05T10:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2017-03-05T10:00:00-05:00</updated><id>/writing/ABriefHistoryOfBioinformatics</id><content type="html" xml:base="/writing/ABriefHistoryOfBioinformatics/">&lt;p&gt;Alright, I have a question for you. If I tell you I am a genomic biologist,
where do you expect I spend most of my time?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;In a lab surrounded by chemicals wearing a white lab coat&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;At a desk, on a laptop smacking my head against a keyboard&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you answered #2, you’re right! But, if you answered 1, that’s pretty
understandable. Biology has changed more than almost any other branch of
science in the last 20 years. It takes many people by surprise when they learn that I predominantly work on a computer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How did this happen you might ask? Where are all the Jane Goodalls of the world
sitting in blinds watching chimpanzees? The Darwins traveling through uncharted lands and jungles, collecting new specimens? The
1950’s era scientist in their white lab coats and horn rims? And finally, why
have all of these people been replaced by a nerd wanting to talk to me about
programming languages and algorithms? Well, to understand this evolution and
this paradigm shift, you first need to understand a brief history of about how 
we got here (don’t worry, it’ll be a quick recap, I promise).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Alright, stop me if you’ve heard this story before. DNA was discovered in the
1950’s by two older white men (LINK) who stole some really important data from
a female scientist(LINK). Once it was confirmed that this molecule was the basis of all life, we began trying to understand how it shaped all life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;DNA research initially was slow. Scientist at the time were working
with limited tools, and no way of replicating DNA in large quantities.
So, while we knew DNA was the molecule of inheritance, we knew little
about how it actually worked at all. But, for a great recap of the how
we came to learn about how DNA, RNA, and protein came together, check
out these links LINK LINK LINK. They do a far better job than I could
at the moment of explaining some of these early breakthroughs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the 1970’s however, a massive breakthrough occurred. Fredrick Sanger(LINK) created a
methodology which allowed for scientist to make lots of DNA at once. But this came with a new problem… How do I analyze all of these new DNA copies? How do I
compare my DNA to the DNA of a tree, or a chimp? Well, initially to
understand the contents of DNA, to get down to the level of A’s, T’s,
G’s, and C’s you had to do quite a bit of chemistry, and then analyze
something like this…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;PICTURE&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If the above photo makes very little sense to you, don’t worry. These types of photos hardly make sense to anyone anymore. Quickly, people realized that the above method of comparison was inefficient and limiting. If it was challenging comparing two slightly different pieces od DNA, comparing a genomes worth, 3.1 billion nucleotides, would be impossible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Early on we had some idea of how much DNA is in a human cell using flow cytomatry, and we established that it was probably arounda  few billion base pairs. So if it took weeks or months to get the sequence of a strand of DNA that was 500 base pairs long, the idea of sequencing all of the DNA of an organisms seemed like a pipe dream. )&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But in comes our heroin, a scientist by the name of Margaret Dayhoff. Dayhoff did something that changed science and biology forever. She created a computer program to help us read and analyze biological data. And thus, the field of bioinformatics was born. Not out of a random act, but out of neccesity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While all this work was being done, the idea of genomics in the mid 1990’s, was still an idea reserved for sci-fi novels and speculative fiction writers. The idea of sequencing the whole of an organisms DNA still far off. But all of a sudden, something changed. The government decided to pour a bunch of money into a first of its kind research, the human genome project.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, bioinformatics was born. Not out of a happy coincidence. But by
a group of men and women well aware that to tackle this problem. To
understand who we are and what we are, we needed to utilize every tool
available to us. And it&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before I begin I just want to make one thing very clear. Bioinformatics is a
huge field. At the time I am writing this, it is a tool and skill set being
used in almost every realm of biology. From Cellular biology, all the way up to
developmental biology. It’s everywhere. And the tools that one computational
biologist uses might be totally different than another. )&lt;/p&gt;</content><summary>Alright, I have a question for you. If I tell you I am a genomic biologist,
where do you expect I spend most of my time?</summary></entry></feed>
