<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><generator uri="http://jekyllrb.com" version="3.1.6">Jekyll</generator><link href="/atom.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2017-03-08T15:39:54-07:00</updated><id>/</id><title>Generally Biology</title><subtitle>A blog about computer science, biology, and everything else</subtitle><entry><title>What is Bioinformatics?</title><link href="/writing/WhatIsBioinformatics/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="What is Bioinformatics?" /><published>2017-03-05T08:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2017-03-05T08:00:00-07:00</updated><id>/writing/WhatIsBioinformatics</id><content type="html" xml:base="/writing/WhatIsBioinformatics/">&lt;p&gt;Alright, I have a question for you. If I tell you I am a genomic biologist,
where do you expect I spend most of my time?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;In a lab surrounded by chemicals wearing a white lab coat&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;At a desk, on a laptop smacking my head against the keyboard&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you answered 2, you are correct! But, if you answered 1, don’t worry about
it. I barely understood what genomic biologist did when I was in college
learning this stuff. But it takes many people by suprise when they
initially learn that what I predominitly do with my day is either creating or
running software on my computer to answer biological questions. How did this
happen you might ask? Where are my nerds in white with pipettes and beakers
doing &lt;em&gt;real&lt;/em&gt; science? And why is this nerd wanting to talk about algorithms with me? Well, let me tell you a brief story about how we got here (don’t worry,
it’ll be a quick recap, I promise).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Alright, stop me if you’ve heard this story before. DNA was discovered in the
1950’s by two older white men (LINK) who stole some really important data from
a female scientist. Once this happened, the race was on to understand how DNA, this silly little chemcial defined what makes us different from a tree.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Initially, we only focused on learning understanding how to make more DNA to
study. After some intensive research Fredrick Sanger(LINK) created a methaology
which allowed for scientist to make lots of DNA copies to study. But this came
with a new problem… How do I analyze all of these new DNA copies? How do I
compare my DNA to a tree? Well, intitially DNA comparison looked something like this…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;PICTURE&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If the above photo makes very little sense to you, don’t worry. These types of photos hardly make sense to anyone anymore. Quickly people realized that the above method of comparison was inefficient and limiting. Early on we had some idea of how much DNA is in a human cell using flow cytomatry, and we established that it was probably arounda  few billion base pairs. So if it took weeks or months to get the sequence of a strand of DNA that was 500 DNA pairs long, the idea of sequencing all of the DNA of an organisms seemed like a pipe dream.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But in comes our heroin, a scientist by the name of Margaret Dayhoff. Dayhoff did something that changed science and biology forever. She created computer programs to help us read and analyze biological data. And thus, the field of bioinformatics was born. Not out of a random act, but out of sheer neccesity due to the absurdly large data problem now looming in the not too distant future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While all this work was being done, the idea of genomics in the mid 1990’s, was still an idea reserved for sci-fi novels and speculative fiction writers. The idea of sequencing the whole of an organisms DNA still far off. But all of a sudden, something changed. The government decided to pour a bunch of money into a first of its kind research, the human genome project.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While genomes had been sequenced before, they were generally limited to either
very small organisms, or human organelles (The little machines in your cells
that allow them to work). But the human genome project was the first of its
kind that proposed the idea of sequencing a large genome, a genome that
comprised 3.1 billion DNA bases. As a comparsion, before the human genome was
proposed, one of the largest things that had been sequenced was the human
mitochondria (the powerhouse of the cell) which had just over 16,000 DNA bases.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, 3 billion dollars, and so many years later.)&lt;/p&gt;</content><summary>Alright, I have a question for you. If I tell you I am a genomic biologist,
where do you expect I spend most of my time?</summary></entry><entry><title>Getting Started in Bioinformatics</title><link href="/bioinformatics/GettingintoBioinforamtics/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Getting Started in Bioinformatics" /><published>2017-03-05T08:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2017-03-05T08:00:00-07:00</updated><id>/bioinformatics/GettingintoBioinforamtics</id><content type="html" xml:base="/bioinformatics/GettingintoBioinforamtics/">&lt;p&gt;So, you’ve read about it, researched it, looked into what it entails, and you
think bioinformatics might be the field for you. Well, great! It’s an amazing
field of science. One undergoing some tremendous growth, and has the potential
to revolutionize the field of biology, medicine, and human health. But… Now
you’re left with an issue. Where do you start?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Honestly, this isn’t an easy question. Bioinformtics is not a field in which
you can take a single coursera course and be good to go. Rather, bioinformatics
is a massive field where there is a seemingly limitless amount of information
to cram in your very limited brain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, rather than attempt to do the impossible and write an extensive guide to
being a genome wizard, I’m going to instead write a little about some resources
I used to get started in the field as well as a little about what you should be
getting from each piece.&lt;/p&gt;</content><summary>So, you’ve read about it, researched it, looked into what it entails, and you
think bioinformatics might be the field for you. Well, great! It’s an amazing
field of science. One undergoing some tremendous growth, and has the potential
to revolutionize the field of biology, medicine, and human health. But… Now
you’re left with an issue. Where do you start?</summary></entry><entry><title>I Love making Test Post</title><link href="/bioinformatics/TESTINGEVERYTHING3/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="I Love making Test Post" /><published>2017-02-23T10:16:01-07:00</published><updated>2017-02-23T10:16:01-07:00</updated><id>/bioinformatics/TESTINGEVERYTHING3</id><content type="html" xml:base="/bioinformatics/TESTINGEVERYTHING3/">&lt;p&gt;This post is literally just me making sure I am able to and capable up updating
this site with the things I am going to need to amke it
succeednkdfsjknafdjnkdfajnkdfjknfdjnkafdjknfdjnkafdsjknfdjnkdfsjnkfdajnkdfjnkjdfnkjnkfdsjknfdnkfdjnkadfjnkfadsdfnsdfsadfs
a
‘dsa
dsa
d
sad
as
‘&lt;/p&gt;</content><summary>This post is literally just me making sure I am able to and capable up updating
this site with the things I am going to need to amke it
succeednkdfsjknafdjnkdfajnkdfjknfdjnkafdjknfdjnkafdsjknfdjnkdfsjnkfdajnkdfjnkjdfnkjnkfdsjknfdnkfdjnkadfjnkfadsdfnsdfsadfs
a
‘dsa
dsa
d
sad
as
‘</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="{&quot;teaser&quot;=&gt;&quot;pexels-photo-90807.jpeg&quot;, &quot;feature&quot;=&gt;&quot;plant-photo-1.jpeg&quot;}" /></entry><entry><title>Welcome to Jekyll!</title><link href="/bioinformatics/TESTINGEVERYTHING2/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Welcome to Jekyll!" /><published>2015-11-17T15:16:01-07:00</published><updated>2015-11-17T15:16:01-07:00</updated><id>/bioinformatics/TESTINGEVERYTHING2</id><content type="html" xml:base="/bioinformatics/TESTINGEVERYTHING2/">&lt;p&gt;You’ll find this post in your &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;_posts&lt;/code&gt; directory. Go ahead and edit it and
re-build the site to see your changes. You can rebuild the site in many
different ways, but the most common way is to run &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;bundle exec jekyll serve&lt;/code&gt;,
which launches a web server and auto-regenerates your site when a file is
updated.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To add new posts, simply add a file in the &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;_posts&lt;/code&gt; directory that follows the
convention &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;YYYY-MM-DD-name-of-post.ext&lt;/code&gt; and includes the necessary front
matter. Take a look at the source for this post to get an idea about how it
works.&lt;/p&gt;</content><summary>You’ll find this post in your _posts directory. Go ahead and edit it and
re-build the site to see your changes. You can rebuild the site in many
different ways, but the most common way is to run bundle exec jekyll serve,
which launches a web server and auto-regenerates your site when a file is
updated.</summary></entry><entry><title>WOOP WOOP ICP</title><link href="/writing/TESTINGEVERYTHING/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="WOOP WOOP ICP" /><published>2015-11-17T15:16:01-07:00</published><updated>2015-11-17T15:16:01-07:00</updated><id>/writing/TESTINGEVERYTHING</id><content type="html" xml:base="/writing/TESTINGEVERYTHING/">&lt;p&gt;You’ll find this post in your &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;_posts&lt;/code&gt; directory. Go ahead and edit it and
re-build the site to see your changes. You can rebuild the site in many
different ways, but the most common way is to run &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;bundle exec jekyll serve&lt;/code&gt;,
which launches a web server and auto-regenerates your site when a file is
updated.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To add new posts, simply add a file in the &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;_posts&lt;/code&gt; directory that follows the
convention &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;YYYY-MM-DD-name-of-post.ext&lt;/code&gt; and includes the necessary front
matter. Take a look at the source for this post to get an idea about how it
works.&lt;/p&gt;</content><summary>You’ll find this post in your _posts directory. Go ahead and edit it and
re-build the site to see your changes. You can rebuild the site in many
different ways, but the most common way is to run bundle exec jekyll serve,
which launches a web server and auto-regenerates your site when a file is
updated.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="{&quot;feature&quot;=&gt;&quot;dnaimage.jpg&quot;, &quot;teaser&quot;=&gt;&quot;dnaimage.jpg&quot;}" /></entry><entry><title>MORE BIOOO</title><link href="/writing/IHAVENOCLUE/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="MORE BIOOO" /><published>2015-10-01T16:16:01-06:00</published><updated>2015-10-01T16:16:01-06:00</updated><id>/writing/IHAVENOCLUE</id><content type="html" xml:base="/writing/IHAVENOCLUE/">&lt;p&gt;Trying&lt;/p&gt;</content><summary>Trying</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="{&quot;feature&quot;=&gt;&quot;forest.jpg&quot;}" /></entry></feed>
